Good to see you again, Astro.
>> Thanks for having me.
>> Uh pleasure, pal. And we've known each
other for God knows a couple of decades
now.
You know, I think most people don't know
something about you. It's worth
mentioning just for fun, since we're
talking about genetics.
Uh his maternal grandfather was a Nobel
laureate in economics, and his paternal
grandfather was Edward Teller,
the creator of the hydrogen bomb. It's
pretty interesting fact.
>> No pressure.
>> It was It was It was a high-pressure
childhood, yes.
>> Yeah, I I guess so.
So, um let me let me kick off the first
question. So, you've been in the
moonshot business for over 20 years.
Uh
walk us through your advice of what it
actually takes to come up with a
moonshot and launch a moonshot. You
know,
how do you make this real? We've got a
lot of individuals here who are here
because they believe in optimism, they
believe in moonshots.
You know, in 10 seconds. No, just
kidding. Uh
what's your advice? I mean, you've
learned so much.
>> Let Let me Let me give you two quick
things. The first one is, let's just
define moonshot, at least how we think
of a moonshot.
>> Which is how I think of it as well.
>> Excellent.
>> from you.
>> So, three basic components. First, there
has to be a huge problem with the world
that you can name and you want to solve.
If you can't name the huge problem, then
it's arguably an academic exercise.
Second, there has to be some kind of
science-fiction sounding product or
service that, no matter how unlikely it
is you could make it, we could pre-agree
that if you made that science-fiction
sounding product or service, it would
resolve that huge problem with the
world. And then, three, there has to be
some kind of breakthrough technology
that gives us a prayer, at least a tiny
chance, at minimum, of being able to
make that science-fiction sounding
product or service and resolving that
huge problem with the world. When you
have that, we would call that a moonshot
story hypothesis.
That does not mean you're going to win,
but at least means it's testable.
The second thing I would say is
like one of the fundamental issues that
we found at X is that you have to have
two things in equal amounts in order to
be a moonshot explorer, to be a moonshot
team. The first one is you have to have
very high audacity. You have to be
willing to suspend your disbelief for
non-stupid reasons
and go on unlikely journeys that might
actually profoundly help the world. But
the second thing you have to have in
equal measure is humility. You have to
know from the first moment you set out
on that unlikely journey that it's
unlikely because if you don't, you will
go ruinously far down that path before
you find out that that is one of the 99%
that just isn't going to work out. So,
being able to say right at the
beginning, "I'm proud that I'm trying
this, but it probably won't work. Let me
learn as fast and as cheaply as I can
whether this is even possible." allows
you to get onto the next moonshot when
that moonshot's not the right one to do.
>> So, your advice for folks, I mean, at
with the challenge of picking a
moonshot, I mean, right now the speed at
which you can
test things, create things, right? But
what about the beginning, choosing the
idea? Any advice there?
Well, I mean, let me put it this way.
What do you do to shut down an idea
quickly?
>> So, sometimes the idea is just not big
enough. Sometimes the idea is too
reasonable or likely to succeed.
Sometimes it's just not good for the
world or the potential for too many sort
of secondary problems associated with it
is just too high.
Uh often it's techno-economics. I cannot
tell you the number of moonshots that
feel so good to people in the early
days. Often these are very technical
people and it's not until you say,
"Really? Like let's go step by step.
What is the best case scenario for the
build of materials that you would make
this from?
What is like just the raw cost in weight
of the stuff that would go into that?
What are people really going to pay?
Could this even plausibly
zero
>> uh first principle thinking in that
regard.
>> Right. First principles thinking about
the techno-economics. You can often kill
moonshots in the very early days because
it's just not going to turn into an
enduring business and at least what I
believe is that purpose and profit can
support each other and then if you're
doing something that's going to lose
money, it's probably not going to change
the world.
>> Yeah.
>> Dave
>> Yeah, I'm really curious about
you know
Alex and Peter have this
solve everything book. It's phenomenal
but the rate at which physics and
material science chemistry is going to
change just astronomically accelerating.
So when you joined Google what 25
23 years ago? How long ago?
>> Uh 16 and a half years ago is I
co-founded X 16 and a half years
>> 16 and a half years ago. Okay. And at
the time it was about a 30 billion
dollar company?
>> Ish. Yes. It was It was very sweet. It
was very small back then.
>> Yeah. A little 30 billion dollar
company. Now just about half a trillion
dollar company. So the scale of R&D in a
corporate environment like that has
grown
miraculously. Just absolutely
tremendously. And I think you were
saying backstage that
the ideal target for a new idea 100
ideas a year
two of them succeed.
>> That's right. We we start one to 200
ideas a year that make it far enough
that they end up with a code name. I who
knows how many we actually look at but
one to 200 ideas a year that are make it
far enough we get a code name. Of those,
about 5 to 6 years later, we graduate to
moonshots out of X.
>> Wow. So, 2% hit rate.
>> And so then if you know if if AGI is
imminent and the idea rate
>> No, it's here.
>> is astronomically
>> Right.
>> Does does that grow on that same
exponential curve? Just that the number
of things at the front of the funnel go
from 100 to 1,000 to 10,000 to
>> Oh, for sure. I mean, there's no
shortage of problems with the world.
There's no shortage of creative ideas
for running at those problems. I think
AI is going to somewhat shrink that time
from a crazy idea to us having de-risked
it to the point where we can say
definitively here's evidence it's not a
crazy idea anymore. So, that's getting
shorter. I hope that AI is going to let
us raise our audacity even higher, so
we'll be shooting higher, and so we'll
be able to do more in a shorter amount
of time. But I'm But fundamentally, I
think the structure will be
>> May I think I think uh you know, if you
asked me 3 years ago, you know, what are
the big things that came out of out of
X, uh Waymo is at the top of the list.
Um Google Google Brain
>> So, that's what I was going to ask
about. So, Google Brain was probably
like, "Ah, yeah, this is cool." Up until
some point a couple years ago when it
was like, "No, this is the entire future
of Google now."
>> guys just spent 80% of the last 3 hours
talking about the stuff that arguably
like Google Brain sort of birthed into
the
>> What What is Google Brain? Define it
because we You know DeepMind, but we
don't know Google Brain.
>> So, Google Brain, uh which started at X
15 and a half years ago or so, was one
of the earliest things that we started.
At the time, there were a set of
academics who were kind of out of vogue.
This was like Andrew Ng, Yann LeCun, a
few others who were saying, "I think
scale might matter." And neural nets
were absolutely dead in the field at the
time. And they're saying, "I think scale
might matter. It it actually bring
neural networks back. And everyone else
in the field said, Nope, you're crazy.
Andrew Ng came to Google X at the time,
and we set up
what it was what was called Google Brain
with Jeff Dean. So, the two of them
paired together to say, What if we
industrialized
neural networks? What if we made them
tens of thousands of times bigger than
anyone had ever done before? Could that
actually be the breakthrough that
everyone's been waiting for? So, we were
the first ones who really made what Fast
Forward
>> called deep learning.
>> TPUs ultimately came from Google Brain.
The Transformer, which is sort of
underpins everything, it's literally the
T in ChatGPT, that came from Google
Brain. So,
you know, our job is to make the seed
crystals that ultimately go on to change
the world, and I think Google Brain
counts as one of them.
>> But there must have been a long period
of time there where that was kind of
quaint and promising, and then a period
of time just a recently where it's like,
Holy crap, that was a lot more than
quaint and promising.
>> Of course, but I think the reality of
any innovation is it takes a super long
time. Every single innovation is like
a overnight success that was 15 to 20
years in the making. And just because
the general public only wakes up to it
in year 18 of that slog, it feels like
it happened overnight.
>> Every overnight success after 11 years
of hard work.
>> For sure. And
>> So, Astro, you you think I watched
hundreds of moonshots, evaluated
hundreds. What are a couple of examples
of moonshots that you would like to have
seen that didn't quite make it, didn't
cut the mustard, whatever you would have
loved to have had them come to fruition?
>> I I mean, I have a very long list. I'll
give you two examples, but
>> Sure.
>> we've been working on clean water over
and over again.
If you can make clean water, if you
could pull it from the atmosphere, if
you could desal for a tenth the price,
you have to be able to get to like a
penny a liter all-in cost for it to
really change the world. But we have
almost 3 billion people in the world who
are water stressed, who don't have clean
water to drink. That's going to get
worse as climate change picks up. We're
going to have hundreds of millions of
climate refugees around the world, and
it's often going to start because they
don't have enough clean water. This is
one of the biggest problems to solve.
>> Mhm.
>> But techno-economics
we've done some great work in the space,
but that it's going to be 10 cents a
liter.
>> Nope.
>> Well, we'll stop doing that. Try it
again. So, that's an example of
something we keep coming back to.
Um
>> Two more.
>> Two more, okay. Um being able to uh time
shift and location shift energy. And I
say it that way on purpose because if
you say transmission lines and
batteries, people tend to narrow their
focus in. But being able to time shift
and location shift energy is absolutely
going to change the world. We've taken a
bunch of runs at those. So far, you
know, we haven't been super excited with
what we've found. Education is another
one. Education is not working. It's It's
not working in the developed world. It's
not working in the developing world.
>> [applause]
>> We're going to keep coming back to that
one till we find something cuz that has
got to be one of the sort of most
fundamental moonshots that you could do.
>> Got it.
>> Love it.
>> Alex, please.
>> Yeah, I'd love to talk a bit about the
history of moonshots. So, one of your
grandfathers invented the hydrogen bomb.
And then if if you look at history, and
I I should add maybe humanity was in the
process once upon a time of landing
humans on the moon in actual moonshots.
And then that stopped. Sometime one can
quibble over the chronology, but
arguably depending on which version of
the great stagnation thesis one
subscribes to, there was maybe up to a
50-year period, call it 1970 to
2020-ish. Again, one can quibble at the
margins, when it would seem that there
was, call it a reduced launch velocity
of moonshots from humanity as all. We
stopped landing humans on the moon. We
stopped inventing, arguably, applied
physical innovations, regardless of
their warfare potential or not, like
hydrogen bombs. And then, again,
arguably, sometime around 2020 or so,
plus or minus a few years, moonshots
started again. We got superintelligence
that actually works. We're getting
robots that actually work. Physical
intelligence, so-called, is seeming to
work. We got, arguably, medical
nanotechnology in the form of lipid
nanoparticles that helped to treat a
pandemic. So, a few related
subquestions. One, do you believe, do
you subscribe to any variant of a great
stagnation hypothesis, that there was a
half-century pause in moonshots? And to
the extent you do, another question, how
do we prevent that from happening again?
>> Well, um
the first thing is I know you didn't
maybe intend it that way, but I'm going
to take that as an enormous compliment
and 11-year in the making joke that we
just made. Since we started in 2010 and
you said 2020 several times, exactly my
point is we started literally a moonshot
factory in 2010.
>> you're actually you brought moonshots
back.
>> Well,
yes, to some extent, I would like to
think that I helped to lead
we did.
>> [applause]
>> So,
that's the first half of the answer. And
and yes, I do think that I don't know I
don't think anyone was planning on it
being a stagnation, but I think
functionally we had lost our way a
little bit somewhere between, you know,
you had your Star Trek stuff up here a
little bit.
>> Yes. Somewhere between like the 1960s
and NASA and the inspiration that that
created, there was a period where we
sort of lost the explorer spirit.
>> you think? What do do you have an
ideology, a diagnosis? What do you think
went wrong?
>> I don't know, but but here is a partial
answer to that, and then I want to get
to the future. Here's Can I tell you all
a a dirty little secret? It'll be our
little secret.
Taking moonshots is really, really easy.
>> Huh.
>> It's it's it's laughably easy
if you don't care about efficiency.
You just find some super energetic
people who are sort of delusionally
optimistic, pour a bunch of money on
them, you will absolutely get some
moonshots.
It's just not a very good return on
investment.
And so, I think we had a period, mostly
because of World War II and the Cold
War, where people didn't care about the
return on investment.
>> Yeah.
>> Then there was a period where people
probably still wanted moonshots, but
they cared about the return on
investment, and so there was less of it.
What X has been trying to practice is
making a moonshot factory, being able to
get at that audacity efficiently enough
to systematize the process, not just to
do it a lot, but to do it efficiently so
it is rational for people to put a lot
more money in. And to your point about
the future,
good news, I think, we get approached
now on a weekly basis from some large
company or some country saying they want
to set up their own moonshot factory.
I'm not sure exactly how we can help
them with that, but there is a hunger to
do more of this, and so good news, I
expect you'll see a lot more of it in
the future, not just for that.
>> But Astro, take a second, and there are
a number of people here in the audience
that are running companies that do want
to set up a moonshot factory, and and we
have discussed a little bit about this,
right? Which
Let me paraphrase what I've learned from
you. You're my moonshot mentor here,
uh which is, you know, your core
organization is responsible for
delivering 10% profit year after year.
And And Salim and I have written about
this that your moonshot factory, if you
would, needs to be on the edge of the
organization where your crazy thinkers
exist, right? And you
Again, quoting you, you know, if you
work on anything at 10%, you're fired.
Focus on 10x, the 1,000%. And then have
that side moonshot organization report
directly to the CEO. Is that still the
formulation?
>> Absolutely. You know, I've run the
following experiment. I apologize to
Peter who's uh heard this a bunch.
Salim's probably heard it a few times,
too, but just bear with me for
45-50 seconds.
Choice A, choice B.
Choice A, you can give a a million
dollars of value to your business this
year,
but it's And it's guaranteed. Or B,
choice B, billion, you can give a
billion dollars of value to your
business this year, but it's not
guaranteed. It's one chance in a
hundred. So, A, million guaranteed, B,
billion, one chance in a hundred. Who's
choosing choice A?
All right, almost nobody here, almost
nobody in the world raises their hand.
WHO'S CHOOSING CHOICE B?
WOO! All right, so you all passed the
math test.
It cuz it has 10 times the expected
utility. I've done this with CXOs the
world over. And I've said, "Okay, now
keep your hand up if on their best days,
in your wildest dreams, your manager,
your CEO, your board of directors
actually supports you doing choice B."
>> Yeah.
>> And every hand in the room goes down.
Yeah.
And I say, "You don't need a lecture on
innovation, you need a new manager."
>> Yeah.
>> This So, the formulation The formulation
you just described is exactly right, and
it's because of this thing. You have to
sequester the choice B's to a place
where they're actually wanted and and
the mess that comes with them is
tolerated.
>> This is Lockheed Skunk Works off on the
edge. This is Steve Jobs taking the Mac
team off campus to build it.
>> Exactly.
>> Yeah.
>> The the capability of the human mind to
do this is very hard. There's something
I've been observing over the last few
years, and I'd love for you to comment
on this. Peter wrote about this in
one of his original books, the
demonetization of the world, right? So,
throughout human history, it's always
been true that advanced technologies
cost a lot.
And today, for the first time in human
history, advanced technologies are
cheap. See solar energy, cheap sensors
are cheap, blockchain's open source and
free, etc., etc. This should enable, you
know, for a CFO or for a big company,
when you want to do very something very
disruptive, you had to make a big bet,
put a lot of resources. CFO hated you,
they would defund it as fast as they
could. Today, you can take a portfolio
of very disruptive experiments at the
edge. So, now it just comes down to
mindset, and are you willing to go for
it? Do you agree with that, and how much
are you seeing companies do that?
>> Uh I I do agree. I think it is a
I hear a lot, "Oh, well, Alphabet has
lots of money, and so that's why this is
happening." I guarantee you that is not
why. We have tiny teams. The teams that
graduate from us, Google Brain when they
graduated, they were like 18 people, and
that's pretty normal. We keep our teams
tiny because we want I we I I say to
them all the time is, "I want you to
find a cheat in the video game of life,
a Gordian knot-chopping moment. If you
can't find that, I don't want you
solving things the normal way. I'd
rather you stop and we go find a
different moonshot, cuz that's what
moonshots mean."
So, I believe it is mostly a mindset
issue, and for those of you out there
who are interested in learning more, we
did a masterclass certificate course.
It's about 20 hours if you do all the
work. It's about 3 and 1/2 hours if you
just watch the videos. I encourage
people to go watch. It's on breakthrough
innovation and it will step people
through. It's our secret sauce is not
secret. We're telling people exactly how
to do it.
>> And tonight, Astro, there's an evening
program by your team doing a 50-minute
condensed version of that, you know,
that 10-hour course.
>> Exactly. 7:00 tonight, Joe Sergeant.
It's going to be a lot of fun. It's on
rapid prototyping.
>> Amazing.
>> I'd also love to have maybe better
understand and develop the record on the
economics of moonshots. I I could make
on the one hand an argument that the
real cost of moonshots increases over
time because expectations go up and we
see arduous problems solved left and
right by people sitting on the toilet
casually solving hard problems. I could
make the argument in the opposite
direction that the real cost of
achieving a moonshot is hyper-deflating
because we have super intelligence now
and we can solve lots of hard problems.
I could probably make some sort of
mediocre middle-of-the-road argument as
well. What would be your position on the
long-term economics of the real costs of
moonshots hyper-inflating,
hyper-deflating,
staying the same.
>> Uh I mean, we track because we're
obsessed with the efficiency of getting
at moonshots. We track what it costs for
us to get to our graduates very
carefully and I can tell you that it's
down by about a factor three over the
last 16 years. There's a lot of waste
and complexity and it's a bit of a
lagging indicator. So, some of what
>> Wait, wait, factor of three over the
that that's inflation.
>> No, no,
>> [laughter]
>> it is a factor of three cheaper, just to
be clear. It's a factor
>> Okay. So, but it that factor of three
over 16 years sounds rhymes to me like
10% per year, which or at least market
returns. It may be market returns.
>> Well, we're talking about two different
things. Yeah, I'm talking about the cost
to get to a Waymo. I guarantee you the
value of the Waymo is so huge relative
to not only the cost of developing that
team but developing all of the other
things that didn't work, it is a very
good return on investment. So, I'm not
worried about that. I'm looking at what
does it cost for each individual thing
that makes it all the way through our
process and that is getting cheaper at I
don't know, 10 20% year-over-year,
something like that. Some of that is cuz
we're getting better at our job. Some of
that is we're graduating things a little
bit earlier. A lot of it is because of
artificial intelligence. So, it's a mix
of all of those things. But, it's
cheaper to get to moonshots now than it
was in the past.
>> But, there are some maybe just to
develop this a a little bit more. Some
would argue that to solve some of the
grandest challenges in science and
engineering, it's not going to be like a
sort of a one-shot spiky capability
launch. It's going to be the result of
our economy
macro growth that we we grow our
capacity of our economy holistically and
that enables particular moonshots to
become easier. And when I hear you say
3x cost reduction, presumably in real
terms, over 16 years, that to me, maybe
you take a different position, that to
me sounds basically like just the result
of markets doubling, say, every 10
years. Stock market doubles every 10
years. So, the result of the reduced
cost of moonshots sounds to me like
basically just our economy is capable of
more things and is basically the same
cost.
>> I think you're confusing the the cost to
paint a house with the value of the
house. They're like apples and oranges.
They're not the same thing. I'm talking
about how cheap it is for us to paint
our house, not what the world will pay
for our house.
>> two moonshots a year, Astro? I mean,
why aren't you pushing out 100 baby
moonshot Alphabet companies per year? I
mean, this is about 10x growth, right?
>> True. I mean,
again, if all I cared about was
moonshots and I didn't care about
efficiency, I guess we would do that.
Because I'm obsessed about efficiency,
there is a cultural rhythm and a set of
habits that are really easy to describe,
but fiendishly hard to get people to
practice. Things like playing the long
game, being intellectually honest,
showing up with humility, being a team
player, and not being an egomaniac.
Like, everyone's like, "Yeah, yeah, duh,
everyone wants that." But, just take a
moment and ask yourself super honestly,
is that how your organization really
functions today?
Right, I can hear the laughter, cuz it
isn't. It's not your fault, but someone
would have to be maniacally determined
to create a microcosm in which those
things were actually the adaptive
behaviors in order to do that. That's
what I'm maniacally focused on is create
is the culture engineering necessary to
get people to practice the habits that
drive innovation efficiently.
Fortunately, I know how to do that with
a few hundred people. I don't know how
to do that with a few thousand people.
It's a culture problem. I just don't
know how to solve it.
>> So, Astro, isn't aren't you making the
argument then that the ultimate moonshot
is the meta moonshot of solving the
organizational problem of launching more
moonshots?
>> Um, yes, I
I'm going to connect your question with
the way I think about it, which is I
would say the meta moonshot we have been
talking about is the meta moonshot is
how to systematize radical innovation.
So, to your question then, there is a
meta meta moonshot, which is how to
systematize systematizing radical
innovation.
How to copy and paste moonshot
factories. Which, back to what I was
saying before, the world is coming and
asking us that. We would love to help. I
haven't yet figured out how to do the
meta meta moonshot, but we're excited to
help.
>> Organizational singularity, Salim.
>> Yeah, I think we might be we might have
that uh methodology for you, because
we've been building for 10 years of of
us societal layer. We're now 50,000
people globally on how do you actually
create an environment where you can spin
off these things very, very quickly. So,
I think
there it's almost like you've solved the
inner few layers of Stuart Brand's pace
layer thing and we've solved the outer
through love. So,
>> We should talk about that.
>> Dave, you were going to say
>> I'd like to take your exact quote and
say, "Look, you know, if you Hey,
dirty little secret, everybody. Doing a
moonshot is really, really easy. You
take fanatically focused people who care
about a mission, who are really, really
smart, and you pour money on them.
Great. Now,
there will be a world where you swap out
the people and you swap in AGIs, and you
take out the money and you pour compute
on them.
That world isn't here yet. There's got
to be some transition world we're in
right now where
there are three AIs and three people,
and I poured compute and money on them.
And then there's another ratio, and
there's Have you Have you started down
that journey yet?
>> Totally. I mean,
All right. I mean, I connect your
question to like a side rant.
On the one hand, if someone came to you
and said, "I want to pitch you my
company. Are you ready for my pitch?
We use electricity."
You would think I was nuts.
Like, on the one hand, you'd be
frightened if I didn't use electricity
in my business, but you'd be like, "So
what? That's an implementation detail.
What are you doing?"
>> Yeah.
>> I feel the same way about AI. I actually
try to say AI as little as possible, cuz
it's it's driving me crazy the way I
>> We should say SI now, super
intelligence.
>> [laughter]
>> Sorry, I I I got a PhD 30 years ago in
artificial intelligence, so a little
stuck on that one. But,
>> Me too.
>> Uh
on the one hand, like what you just
described, every one of our moonshots,
that's it. It's a bunch of agents and a
bunch of people working together to try
to solve a problem. That's an
implementation detail. What we're
obsessed with is the problem, whether
it's clean water or it's a way to make
grid-scale energy storage or it's
education, whether it's how to fix the
electric grid, how to make our world
serve actually circular so we're not
sending trillions of dollars a year to
landfill. Like those are the things that
we're obsessed about. And then in the
background, yeah, it's humans and agents
like making it happen. But most of our
obsession is the problem and like how to
couple that into a business so that it
gets bigger over time, so it doesn't
cost too much. Let me try
>> that into a budget question. So if you
said here, clean water is a great one,
great you know, moonshot. I need What
was it like a a penny a liter or about a
penny a liter to really change the
world? Okay, so that's a great moonshot.
If if I said, let's turn Have you
already got a team on that one? Is that
>> We have had teams on them in the past. I
Yes, we do have a team on it right now.
>> Okay, okay. So is there What's bigger,
their AI bill or their salary bill?
>> It's still their salary in that
particular case, but yeah, I don't know
by how much, honestly. So
I I don't know what fraction it is for
sure, but I would say they're absolutely
teammates in the process of innovation.
And in fact,
you know, we are finding ways all the
time to automate parts of the moonshot
factory so we can go faster and be more
efficient.
>> Your best guess then, you know, if
you're you're hyper-focused on the
efficiency of that innovation machine,
there's a case study. Right now their AI
bill is smaller than their head count
bill.
When's the day when it hits 50/50,
75% AI and then 100%?
>> Well, first of all, I'm not sure anytime
in the next decade it's going to be 100%
because I think figuring out which
problems to solve and making sure
they're being solved in societally
acceptable ways is an important part of
the problem. If you need to have
distributors helping to sell this, if
you have to land it in communities in
ways that that community feels are
acceptable to them, like you need humans
as part of that process for at least the
next decade or two.
>> Okay.
>> So,
but look, it'll go as as fast as is
efficient. Like, we're not going to use
compute just to use compute. And there
were people who are spinning up agents
because it feels powerful to spin up
agents. But, there is a difference
between spinning up an agent actually
getting benefit.
>> Mhm.
>> Astro, you go ahead, Salim.
>> Yeah, there's I think of moonshots as
two classes. Okay.
>> Okay.
>> uh pain points. Solve hunger, solve
education, solve whatever. And then
there's the aspirational moonshots.
Elon, get us to Mars, right? Uh um um
solve aging, etc. How much of your work
in moonshots focuses on one versus the
other? Is it an equal balance? Or do you
focus only on the problem side?
>> I mean, if you worked at X, what I would
say is, Jason, can't I have both? I want
you to find the most audacious things
you can work on that we can move from
crazy idea to not crazy idea in less
than a decade. And then from not crazy
idea to an enduring business in less
than another decade. So, if you want to
go to Mars, I would start with, "Okay,
I'm listening. How is that in less than
two decades going to be an enduring
business?" I'm not saying it can't, but
that would be my task.
>> So, it's time your time you're
constraining yourself just so you can
give a sense of
if we can reliably work on this problem
over this next decade and spin out
something that becomes the main
criteria.
>> Because
>> That makes sense.
>> because I'm getting money. Our investor
is Alphabet. I have to tell Alphabet,
"Here's what I'm doing with your money."
And they have to feel good about the
sort of flywheel that I'm creating for
them. That's
>> Astro, one of the things I find
fascinating is the the fact that you
kill the vast majority of the ideas that
are started. Just to give us some
numbers here, total number of projects
started versus graduated,
it's
under 1%?
>> Uh
I think it's close to 2% but call it
like 2,000 things over the last 16 years
that got code names of which we've had,
a little bit depending on how you count,
sort of 35 to 50 graduates.
>> So, talk about this idea of the
importance of killing your babies early.
>> Well, um
>> No, not not his actual babies.
>> Yes, I I I'm going to use I'm going to
use the monkey and pedestal analogy
>> Please, don't.
>> you know well, but imagine we were
working on a moonshot together, all of
us, and we were trying to get a monkey
to stand on the top of a 10-ft pedestal
and recite Shakespeare.
Which should we do first? Train the
monkey or build the pedestal?
It is so weirdly tempting, if we're
being honest with each other, in
something where it's not that extreme a
situation, to build the pedestal, cuz
then you're half done, and you can get
another round of funding, live to fight
another day. You can go to your boss and
say, "Can I have a promotion? I'm half
done, man. Can I Can I have a bonus?"
This is what drives the world, and it
drives me crazy.
So, what we say at X is
forget the pedestal, only focus on the
monkey. If you can train the monkey, we
can always build a pedestal afterwards,
and if you can't train the monkey, thank
god we didn't waste Alphabet's money and
our time on that. And so, it's not that
I want to lose. I am like the crown
prince of failure, but it's not because
I like to fail, it's because you learn
nothing when you're right.
You only learn things when you're wrong.
>> [applause]
>> I love it.
Crown prince of failure, love it.
>> And so, if you accept, which it sounds
like you do, that that's true, and
moonshots is a process almost entirely
taken up with learning, then we're going
to go on an adventure, which is defined
entirely by how fast we learn, which
means if we in any way feel bad in the
moment where we learn because we had a
model of the world that turned out to be
wrong in some way, then we will
unconsciously or maybe even consciously
avoid that moment. So, we're going to
de-stigmatize failure. If you work at X,
I need you to be on the mission with me
to optimize X's portfolio.
It's not that I don't want the
teleporter to work, Peter, who's working
on this for me,
but I want to find out as efficiently as
possible if it's going to work. I don't
want you in denial about the fact that
you just really want the the teleporter
to work and we go for like 5 years and
we spend tens of millions of dollars and
it's still kind of going sideways and
it's a zombie. How many people have you
here have spent at least 5 years on
something that was a zombie where you
knew for at least 2 or 3 years that it
was a zombie.
>> What's the What's the worst the worst
failure? Like the the failure where you
were like that's really crazy and turns
out, you know what? That really was
really dumb.
>> Oh, we've had
>> [laughter]
>> lots of those. We We have one right now
which is almost certainly wrong. Um it
would
be a
a problem for physics if it turned out
to be right.
So, um but it's it's working. We do not
know why it's working in the lab. We're
working ferociously hard to find why
we're kidding ourselves so that we can
kill it off. But it's about 5 months
into trying to discover this sort of
like cold fusion moment, which I hate.
Cold fusion, it's not cold and it's not
fusion. But [laughter]
>> It's okay, good. It didn't work anyway.
It's all right.
>> we don't want to be that group, right?
We are trying to be the opposite of that
group.
>> going to tell us what this thing is?
>> Nope.
>> Oh, come on.
>> Okay, if it works out, we'll tell you
about it.
>> All right. So, uh
>> We have one right now that's like makes
me deeply uncomfortable and deeply
excited.
>> Okay, a couple audience questions here.
Rich asked, are there any moonshots that
you regret denying in the past as our
world's problems have changed, that you
would pursue today.
>> I mean, we were wrong a bunch. So, I'm
about to say no to that question, but I
do not want that to be confused with
we've never been wrong. We're wrong all
the time.
>> the question though the question
>> Do I regret it though?
>> But do you it was something that you
reject you never even try. Okay.
>> So, I want to be really clear. The cost
for a false positive where we believe
it's a moonshot, we run it for many
years, and then it turns out not to be
is very high, many tens of millions of
dollars potentially.
>> Yeah.
>> The cost of a false negative where it
actually is a moonshot, but I rejected
it is zero.
As long as you believe that there's an
infinite number of problems in the world
and an infinite number of creative
solutions, we can always just go draw
again from the distribution of
moonshots. It costs us nothing to say
no.
So, I say no and have no regrets even
about the stuff we were wrong about.
>> We probably don't do it fast enough.
>> Paul asks, "What about moonshots and
material sciences?
Uh do you see any particular promising
fields to inquire in that area?"
>> Well, I mean, side rant, I'm super
excited about the new material space.
>> Yeah.
>> And I think people haven't played out in
their minds cuz there's like such a
fervor about the technology and
everyone's like, "And then we'll make a
business out of it."
Yeah, that's harder than it sounds. Look
how many centuries it took for us to
really refine steel. Steel completely
changed the world, but not until it was
industrialized in a bunch of ways.
>> Mhm.
>> There are a lot of new materials that if
you could make one flake of room
temperature superconductor, that would
be pretty cool, Nobel Prize, yay.
That is not a business. That's like the
first 5% of a business. How do you make,
you know, thousands of tons a day of
that material. How do you make it with
very high ductility so that you could
put it into like winding wires and
things like that?
>> Yeah.
>> All of the stuff that it takes, the
other 95% of the work for new materials
or otherwise, that's what it really
takes to make a moonshot. So, I'm super
excited about lots of things like new
materials, but I'm kind of focused on
the hill after the one that people are
focused on, which is how would we scale
these up as they show up in the world?
Not just how do we find them in the
first place?
>> All right, last quick question from the
audience and a quick answer, hopefully.
So, other companies keep trying to
replicate X
and fail.
What's the single hardest piece for them
to replicate that you think most outside
observers still underestimate?
>> I really believe it's what I said, which
is you have to have a leadership team
that is maniacally focused on
engineering a culture in which people
can show up in the ways that tend to
drive radical innovation most
efficiently. And, if I can make a plug,
just like you have a moonshot podcast,
we have a moonshot podcast. There are
two seasons out now where you can
actually hear about people who went
through the process. So, this is not me
blah blah blah-ing about moonshots, it's
actually the moonshot takers talking
about their successes in
>> find it? On YouTube?
>> If you just search for moonshot factory
moonshot podcast, you can find it
anywhere you get podcasts. And I would
encourage people to listen to this
because I think what you'll hear is a
reflection of exactly what I said, which
is the culture, the microcosm which
encourages people to do the things that
actually drive innovation.
It's it's obvious, you all know what it
is, it's making that space, that
protected space for those explorers,
that's the really hard part.
>> I I would like to say something to
answer that question. Um you have
created a mechanism where you've
structured it such that the mothership
has left you alone for a long period of
time. I've never seen another company do
it. Every other company I've ever seen,
over time the immune system cannot
resist, reaches out its sticky little
hands, and snatches it back, and then
messes it up invariably. So,
congratulations to you for having lasted
this long, and congratulations to the
Google execs who have left it and had
the discipline to leave it on the edge,
because that's where all the magic
happens.
>> Hey everybody, give it up for Astro
Teller.
>> [music]